software engineering radio episode 92
introduction to game development this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at se - radio dotnet se radio Prince
irrelevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on soft engineering topics
every 10 days thanks to our audience and
the partners listed on our website for
supporting the porkchop
[Music]
welcome to software engineering radio
this is episode 92 introduction to games
with Oliver you cannot interviewed by
Elmo in this episode we are
experimenting with a message from a
sponsor in this and the next three
episodes will have a short message from
author a German consulting company at
the end they are trying to find a bunch
of additional consultants and co-workers
the advertisement is in German so if you
don't speak German you're probably
better skip it otherwise you should
maybe listen please let us know after
these this and the next two episodes
what you think about this kind of
advertising at the end of the episode
whether you think that's useful whether
you think this is OK we've had the the
survey where most of you said it would
be ok but just let us know what you
think thanks and now let's have fun with
the episode this is Arno and today I'm
interviewing Oliver about game
development would you like to say a few
words about yourself before we dig in
yes hello everybody my name is Oliver
yogurt and I've been o programming for
30 years and half of the time I've been
writing computer games and the other
half of the time I've been writing
commercial products mostly in the
enterprise area I enjoy writing computer
games very much and I think it's one
very very special area of programming
that has some traits others don't have
since you have experience on both sides
of the fence maybe we should start by
armed well but you telling us what's
special about writing computer games and
how is it different from writing normal
software like business software some
people who try to write computer games
the way you write normal business
software most times you got some
Hollywood studio that has a lot of money
has some very special characters and
wants to earn some extra money by
writing a computer game most movie
adaptions of computer games are very bad
because they are exactly written in the
typical waterfall method
where you have some requirements up in
the beginning a lot of money and then
you end up with a very very bad game
that's a proven method and is repeated
all over again
I would like to talk about the other way
of writing computer games they start
with the very very simple requirements
right a computer game that gives players
a lot of pleasure and a long long
lasting entertainment some people start
with this requirement and take it
further and further and develop some
creative and starting-point idea into a
very very nice computer game and the
trick about that is you start with this
very simple requirement makes something
that is fun to play and then you have to
work in very very short development
cycles and to always retest what you
have written to get a feedback of the
better testers that you are on or the
right track and that this will end up
with something that is indeed fun to
play this sounds really special I mean
people claim they're doing agile
development in all kinds of projects but
this sounds like game development is one
area where it's actually done that way
how long are the increments typically if
you do this agile psych cycle driven
feedback driven kind of game development
oh about one year for projects that
don't work out and the smaller the
development cycle the higher probability
that you will get a game that's good so
in the very extreme form you have a
cycle from the developer creating a new
feature to the better test or testing it
that's within days so you have cycles of
about typically I would say one week to
week
wow that's pretty pretty short and
sounds pretty cool how much initial
effort do usually usually have to spend
before you have the first thing you can
have hand over to the testers there are
testers and testers some testers I can
incorporate in the development very very
early and then they can test some very
spectacular
triangles moving around on the screens
and
the very very early elements of the game
but for this kind of beta test you need
a lot of abstraction or fantasy to fill
in the gaps that still exist our public
beta testing you have to have the game
nearly finished so I would say the first
one or two better testers start more or
less on the same day as the coda do but
for the big public better testing you
have the game nearly I would say hardly
done ok so you start out with an idea
and you have better testers in place how
about you just sort of take us through
the development cycle of a game so you
start up with an idea you want to get
the game finished and you have ideas
you've got friends who volunteer to be
the better testers who else do you need
and how do you start having a good idea
is a very good starting point just
getting together or let's write a
computer game that beats all the other
stuff it's not a good starting point you
need some idea of about writing about
your writing you are writing the next
generation shoot him up third person
shooter or whatever this idea has to be
a vision that's common to the core team
if you look at the list of person that
worked on a game you see on modern games
about 100 persons sometimes only 50 but
it's a lot of them if you have a closer
look at these teams you always find out
that there is a small core team and
that's typically less than 8 people so 5
to 7 people that has started with a
vision of how this game should be on how
this game should look like typically
there is one creative person if you have
good luck sometimes you have two or
three persons drawing the game in two
different directions which is not a
speed-up factor so having more creative
people at the very beginning is even a
disadvantage but this core team has to
share a vision where they want to go
this vision is typically not what you
end up in the final game but this has to
be strong enough to carry you along all
these beta testers which tell you that
it doesn't work and it doesn't work
again and this worked isn't doesn't work
neither you have to survive this so you
have to have one vision that gives you a
where you want to go to if you gather
then some programmers around you and
some of the programmers typically take
over the role of the very first beta
testers you should also think of the
artwork in the very very beginning
because games are the most visual things
you can develop and without any artwork
it doesn't work at all and the artwork
is not just an add-on the artwork
influences the game the game story
whatever you have in your mind so
typically the programmers start with a
set of functionality they can provide
and the art people say ok that's exactly
what we need and then they produce a lot
of artwork that doesn't work with your
library and you have to enhance your
library and as soon as you have enhanced
it enough to face what they have created
the last time they get some very very
interesting new ideas that don't work at
all with your new libraries and so the
art development always pushes the
program developers ahead on the other
hand the program developers can pull the
art of our people to produce very very
interesting and fantastic thing the art
people didn't think about it for this
kind of work you need very special
artists the typical artists can't do
this ok so obviously you need
programmers you need a vision you've got
the testers and you've got visual
artists who else is on the team I mean
there's a big gap between 5 to 8 people
and 100 people who else is on the team
more artists more programmers or more
better testers no joke for example the
core team is responsible for the core
game that is the game executable you
deliver to the customers but in writing
a computer game you need to write a lot
of more programs you need a level editor
you need textures converters you need a
lot of external programs that can be
delivered by other programming teams and
it's a good idea to split this up as
long as you can keep the development
team size Bulow's let's say 8 people you
can live with a minimum of management
overhead and this management overhead
can kill you
yes sometimes it doesn't work out
sometimes it just costs a lot of time
sometimes some idiot starts with
PowerPoint presentations or Microsoft
how do you call it
this program I never use Microsoft
Microsoft loader yes thank you
we're going to think about game
development
I don't think about this program so you
try to keep several teams but each team
varies a small size and the saying goes
for the artist you have very different
views of art for example you need to the
art for the textures you need to the
arts for the cover of the game you need
3d arts that is computer-generated
completely you need 3d arts that is
scanned from real real objects so 3d
scanners and alone for the 3d scanners
and 3d computer Department you can
always hire an arbitrary number of
people they don't run out of work
so the initial stake stage is getting
the game as far as possible with a few
people that you can recognize what the
game is about and then it comes to the
second phase where you blow it up until
it's very very big and beautiful and
then comes the third phase value again
shut it down until you have a size that
can be reasonable to finance and that
can be developed in a reasonable time
okay so game develop go through these
phases with increased staffing but what
about the insides of the program of a
game
what special what's different in
programming again the most special thing
about writing a computer game is
performance does matter if I write a
program for a very big company web
application 300 layer program and the
program doesn't perform very well as
long as I have it scalable people can
just add hardware and it's most time
it's cheaper to add hardware than to
optimize program for computer games it's
the opposite way around for example if
you write for a console you have a very
limited
computing power compared to current
computers at least you have a limited a
given availability of the hardware power
for triangle calculations and other
stuffs for computer graphics so ya are
not working time boxed or money box
you're working box by the console
capabilities this is one of the last
areas where assembler program still is
alive for example the computer graphics
computer graphics traders are written
assembler or if you have an Intel CPU
you can do a lot of stuff with the SMD
extensions all in assembler so this is
still an area where assembler can matter
and because this is the last area where
performs really does matter
you tend to find a lot of people that
are performance nerds or performance
affine in this area so one of the
biggest problem is to shut down these
people when the game is fast enough I
have had one friend okay I may think I
can quote him by name Michael ah Mart's
who has in a very long time ago written
a delay loop then he has optimized the
delay loop to be faster and this is the
kind of work that is sometimes not
helpful and yes so this is some Drive
you get there this is something where
you can get a lot of fun out of this but
I always propose first letter on your
performance optimizer and to find out
where the performance loopholes are and
so on but then you have all the right in
the world to spend hours and days
writing and rewriting ten lines of
assembler code and this is something I
miss in the other areas
it sounds like computer gaming is one of
the last areas where the lonely hacking
hero still has a right to live there's
another area in the demoscene where
computer programmers try to write as
much graphical Wow and only 10 kilobytes
of codes or something like that
and I would say the computer graphics
and the demoscene
are very impressive but there's always
trouble to make out of money out of
these demos you can say that the
computer writing area is the commercial
part of the demo scene so obvious
performance is a big issue mmm
how do you go about having this
performance first of all you need to
find out where your performance bottles
are and yes this can be very hard
because for example if you're running on
a console game you get limited real-time
support it's really hard work to get out
where your time is running up and
sometimes you have additional fun
because you have a multi CPU systems for
example the cell CPUs or something like
that and they are really really hard to
debug and especially if something goes
wrong 1000 times but fails one times and
produces a jitter in the game you have
to find this jitter my best or worst
parts depending on the view those bars
that introduce a small jitter about
every three minutes
good luck hunting so this is sort of the
debugging approach are there design
approaches that you can take sort of to
to have fluent movement and to deal with
the wider range of different equipment
to make use of fast hardware if you
without overloading weaker hardware yes
in the good old time you need only a
double buffer display to make a fluent
game today it's much more complicated
one of the biggest challenges right now
are the level of detailed systems we got
very early a level of detail for
computer graphics so monster that's far
away only gets three triangles if it's
up front to you you get three million
drawings for that this is more or less
known how this works the next challenge
at the level of detail thing is to give
level of details for behavior so on
stars that's far away I got only one
nanoseconds para monster to calculates
its behavior for this frame so I need
some kind of autistic systems
that gave me an approximation for the
behavior of a herd with very very few
computer time so level of details at
very different level of abstractions is
very very hard to achieve and this is a
challenge the other challenge we right
now face is a technical challenge of
multiprocessor systems these are not
very well understood yet
for example the behavior for monster is
quite hard to distribute on a lot of
systems or a lot of CPUs without running
in deadlock source kind of that and once
again this is very hard to debug when
you talk about problems with
multiprocessor systems this sounds like
multi-threading is used a lot is that
true and why are there so many threads
in game development right now quite the
opposite is true
very very few games can make use of more
than one thread at a time at most three
games or most gamers have machines that
has one fast CPU and you don't get much
of a quad CPU machine right now as a
gamer so this is a challenge this most
computer studios or game studios are
right now working on making their
libraries multi-threading capable and to
use the power of something like cell
CPUs systems or anything like that okay
you're just now talking about the
behavior of a monster what is the
typical representation of a monster or
of the world at large in a game and of
the behavior of things of the look of
games of the constellation whatever are
there recurring patterns of how they are
represented I don't think we have the
time to go down into the lowest levels
of this but yes there are things that
reoccur for example you got always a
separation between the background static
content that changes very very slowly
and they get the fast changing content
let's call that in the monsters a very
interesting thing in this in the
interaction of the monsters with each
other
for example a very simple question is
how can you find the next
monster you can shoot it yes you can
optimize yourself to death to solve this
question the more interesting is if you
have different level of details for
example monster that is on a lower level
of data because it's far away to
interact with the monster that is on a
higher level of detail and that has a
completely bit different behavior for
example imagine a swarm of birds that
crosses some level of detail threshold
and doesn't have an migration process of
going from one level of detail to the
other level of detail so another thing
that's very interesting is the physical
simulation of the world because most
games are involving some kind of
violence and this violence is only fun
because you can see the effects of this
violence and yes the most interesting
thing is to blow something up to destroy
something or something like that to do
it in a special way or in a fascinating
way you have to simulate physics and
once again if it's up to front to you
it's very hard work it's a lot of
computing time so you have again level
of details that you must handle the most
challenging problem there is collision
detection that's always a question for
example if you soo shoot at somebody how
do you in the computer world find out
whether you hit or not one simple
approach is implement right tracing so
the simplest thing is if you want to
shoot at somebody Center into this
direction once you get the rate racing
up and running you get a lot of
additional functionalities for example
you can send rays to detect the behavior
of your underground the simplest thing
is send rays trust down and see how the
ground is the set of the ground ray
tracing can substitute true collision
detection in a lot of cases for example
we don't have any well working wrestling
simulation because if two bodies touch
each other you have to detect where and
how and it's very very hard to simulate
that in a spear and with high enough
speed how
you go about simulating behavior that
makes monsters look intelligent I mean
this sounds like artificial intelligence
to me sort of I don't know if this is
actually what's happens but how do you
go about making monsters appear as if
they behave naturally or decide how they
behave looks quite complex quite natural
to me much of the time but I imagine it
must be sort of simple because otherwise
the computing power wouldn't be enough
how do you go about net the first step
is you watch players playing games if
you can reach the complexity complexity
of a player steering a monster I can't
be happy so the first thing is if you
watch players what do they do the
patterns are simple they stay at tend to
stay hidden and snipe at you or some
players just go ahead and want to have a
maximum of fun so just watching players
you can extract some very very
interesting patterns and yes once you
get the pattern to implement the pattern
yes that's a question of how much
performance you got and sometimes simple
questions like give me my left neighbour
can cost you a lot of computational
power so sometimes you have to scale the
behavior down to something that is
manageable but the first step is start
by looking at players another good
source is look at animals yes
typical animals have no any very animal
has a typical hunting behavior and you
can get a lot of ideas just at looking
at animals in a zoo where they move
around or something like that
another thing is what's very fascinating
is herd behavior so if you have a lot of
monsters and with horizon computing
power we get more and more monsters the
interaction of the Hertz inside the herd
are very important and there's a whole
lot of theory about these things let's
go into some more detail there how do
you simulate a herd of buffalo
stampeding first of all each animal in
the herd
to know its surrounding animals the
first thing is you have to implement a
set of rules and then wait this rule for
example one rule is don't hit the cow
running ahead of me the other thing is
if hit by another cow in my bag I run
faster and these rules are very very
simple all of them the hard thing is to
arrange these rules to make something
that works for example if they work if
their heart hits an obstacle that's a
very very fine art and I don't think
there are book cookbook recites for this
how to do this that's one of the fun
things about writing computer games on
some parts you're just cutting edge if
you don't do something that's not very
very very well known you're doing
something wrong then you are doing it
too simple too easy just make it more
realistic make it more complex to get a
challenge out of this
so you basically model the behavior by
having a list of sort of simple
behavioral rules and then you look at
the results and if you like them it's
okay otherwise you sort of try to find
human the rules but still it remains a
simple set of rules to which you add
something or remove something from it
and then behavior emerges yes that's the
hard way and I would say as far as I
know that's the typical way the
commercial programs do this but just to
give you a new idea one way to solve
this problem is genetics programming if
you interpret this set of rules as a in
a string then you can create new
behaviors quite easily by recombining
them that's not that hard as it sounds
right now just take two bunch of
monsters and let they hit each other
those who wins have got a higher ranking
in the gene pool and after you've done
this sometimes let's say you start with
the gene pool of two year ten DNA
strings after you have done it okay
let's say 30
then you choose the three best of this
pool and recombine them the only thing
to be able to recombine is you need to
start at a point where each rule
sequence makes some kind of sense
otherwise the genetic engineering
doesn't work and you don't get off but
there are some ideas in the genetic
engineering programming area where you
can really steal from and get these
problems solved in real time the good
thing about that approach is you get
some kind of artificial stupidity pulled
in the thing is to will the perfect
killer monster it's not very hard just
points at your head shoots you're dead
so it's more interesting to get
something that has more complexity even
some faults to it only if it has some
interesting behavior behavior you can
look at and you accept as realistic so
this genetic approach I've tried it
sometime gives you some behavior that
looks lifelike even if it's not perfect
how do you go about writing a language
that has recombine herbal blocks where
combination of different blocks make
sense I mean if you just recombine the
elements of AC program in a random
fashion you practically never get a
compatible program so how do you go
about writing a program that can be
genetically recombined that's always if
you are not talking about deeply aspects
of the genetic programming always the
trouble frightened DNA representation
that makes sense if you cut it in half
and recombine it by the way nature this
does or doesn't work very often but
Nature has that one just love trying it
again and again some billion times per
second but with our computer power we
can get quite near to this so you're not
always that hard bound to this that a
recombination of two programs we use and
another you can save a lot of time if
you don't just take sue to see programs
cut them in half and recombine them this
doesn't make fun
I propose take a rule based system where
you got a set of
rules with a lot of parameters these are
very very kind to this kind of approach
and you can recombine to different set
of good building blocks to get a better
monster the theory about genetic
programming is that by arbitrarily
cutting the DNA strings you find good
buildings more blocks and they are
proper propagated and so if you got a
set of say about 100 parameters that
control you monsters then cutting these
100 parameters adding some radioactivity
by randomizing some values works very
very well last year that makes a lot of
sense to give us some idea about the
level of complexity of the game how many
monsters are there typically at the same
time for which for which the behavior
must be tracked by the game in real time
right now this is reversed the other way
around how many monsters can I render in
correct time I would say most games
typically games have about 30 40 100
monsters but I expect when it's number
to rise rapidly to at least 1000 months
or something like that that can we
simulate it in a realistic way because
one problem you get with complex games
is you go somewhere do some demolition
dues affect the monster that live there
go away come back and they are more or
less reset to the original state so we
need to increase the number of monsters
only to if only to get better and
realistic world behavior so now we have
individual monsters 30 or 40 of them now
is thousands of the future but
individual monsters do not make complete
missions levels whatever how do you
combine them how do you make levels play
to fun a fun to play there are two basic
approach the one is the control freak
that places every single monster and
turns it into the right direction and to
have complete control control about the
game that he's writing for example doom
3 was a game where every single monster
was placed in a perfect way these games
are fun to play they have very very nice
affects in a very good level design the
trouble is the costs are very very high
for this approach so you get either very
very expensive games are very small
games and one of the disadvantages of
doom 3 was once you played it you were
finished with this game there was
nothing interesting happening right now
then the other approach is that you
create words virtual worlds where the
player has some tasks to do and you
don't control each feature you need a
lot of more better testing because
sometimes for example if you place two
different kinds of monsters near to each
others they start to fight with each
other and the gamer has just to walk
through so you need more better testing
but you get much more richer levels that
are much more complicated but just
placing monsters together doesn't make a
level every good game design guts
riddles and lots of riddles inside and
the question is how do you create
riddles I myself have found a very
strange and answer to this I have
studied computer science and then
there's a branch on the compare
computational complexity where you rank
problems in different kinds of how much
computational time you need to perform
that to calculate that and one of the
most interesting problems are the
np-complete problems I don't think I can
go up to very deep details but there are
a lot of problems that our guest to need
more than polynomial time a lot of time
short to compute but we are not very
sure about that it's still open question
whether you can compute them in
polynomial time or not this class of
computer games at this class of problems
sorry not yet computer games this class
of problems has one very very
interesting property for computer
developers humans are quite good at
approaching a perfect solution for
example one problem is the travelling
sales man where a traveler has to use it
a little east of given points in the
shortest possible time
most humans are very good at doing an
intuitive gas
that and there's a whole class of about
100 or more documented problems and you
can take these elemental atomic problems
and convert them into computer
challenges there are a lot of problems
that are abstract you can't use but
these half of them can be used to create
problems that are not easy to solve but
where humans are good at getting an
approximation this is some work to do
but this is one of the interesting
problems to get a problem or a task for
the gamer that is hard but not too hard
to solve so how would you incorporate
Traveling Salesman problem in a computer
game easy give the player a ticking
time-bomb in the middle you have 30
seconds and you need three keys to
disarm this time okay I see that so far
we've been talking about single player
games on a console or on a personal
computer but network games multiplayer
games have becoming more and more
popular what's different with them a lot
there are several levels of multiplayer
games one level is that's quite old you
have some people working together sorry
laying together which is quite a behind
word sometimes playing together on the
local network and where you have a high
bandwidth and communication is easy
these games are more and more replaced
with centralized servers that can handle
very huge amounts of players and for
example World of Warcraft has attracted
millions of players right now and there
are a lot of technical challenges at
that
for example the single simple problem of
collision detection in a multi-user
environment is very very hard to solve
because if you have one simple cycle
where every player has to do what he
wants to do send it to the server the
server emulates the world and sends back
the images to each client you get a very
very slow response time so to increase
the response time or at least the
illusion of a fast response time you
have to emulate the world in parallel on
the client computer and on the server
computer
if this emulation is flawed by for
example different behaviors or different
runtimes of the data these models of the
different words differ from each other
so the main server has to sometimes send
the correct image of what is true to
each other player this needs a very
clever algorithm how to synchronize the
clients view or the client computers
view of the world with a true view that
has the central server this is a very
fascinating thing to work at the more
fascinating thing is to test it if you
want to test a simple single computer
user game you can give it to a single
beta tester but if you want to test
whether a server can survive 10,000
users you need 10,000 users because
these 10,000 users try things you can't
imagine up front for example there was a
competition how many people fit into a
single room in world of warcraft
yes this is don't something the
developers don't think of that about
100,000 people try to get into the same
room yes so if you want to make better
testing for multi player games you need
a lot of players let's take a closer
look at this getting out of sync between
the server and the clients why does that
happen I mean it's the same program code
on the server on the chlorines why can't
they get out of sync imagine that there
are two players both firing ahead at a
swarm of Klingons starships shooting at
you
if the Klingon starships are a hurt as
we described it earlier with the cowherd
a single shot at a single ship can
change the behavior of the entire heart
and hurts our chaotic systems so even
the slightest difference in a time when
I shot the first monster produces a
completely different outcome whether for
example the complete hurt turns tail and
runs away or continues to attack okay I
understand that the herd behavior is
chaotic
by what
I should there even be this initial
slight difference in in state that
cancer when you do the coordinator er
escalate what is the initial cause why
do they get out of thing in the first
place
imagine a heart of Klingon starship
approaches two players each player
client has a model of this world on his
own computer and if I do something if I
for example shoot as his first
approaching starship this starship will
react inside my own simulation and then
this event will be propagated to the
other computer so imagine two players
shooting at the first starship
approaching on my computer I shoot at
this chip from the left side so this
starship turns away the other computer
the player starts at the right side so
the computer the starship turns to the
other direction away and the complete
herd follows this first behavior so on
my computer the curse first starship
turned left on the computer of my friend
its turned right on the server in the
middle nothing at all yet happened
because the translations the
transmissions are quite slow then i
propagate my state of the world to the
central server and i told him okay I hit
the first starship and it turned left
the server says good for you but I've
heard from your friend's client computer
that he should also shot at the first
starship and it turned right then you
get to have some kind of solution
so either the Chara starships just jump
around on the screen very very bad
solution or you have some very very
smart algorithm that is able to deliver
very small parts of my reality and then
for very very fast to the server that
the time from start of different
developments to the resolution is very
short you can't probe it this completely
it happens always but the question is
how nice can you get out of this bad
solution for example you can morph this
from a starship around or you can just
explode always a good solution game
design if something is nasty if
something can be not handled in an
effective very effective way
just let it explode and all your
problems are gone this may be a
difference towards commercial
programming we're blowing up some kind
of data store or something like that is
not appropriate so it basically boils
down to
while bandwidth in network communication
is limited you cannot have a single
server in the center so you need to sort
of do incremental synchronization and
then blow things up to get in sync again
they've got too far out of sync okay so
now we took a closer look at the
problems and the differences the
specialties of implementing games but
how do you a gain I understand you mean
user interface design yes the user
interface design of games is very unique
because gamers respond very badly to bad
user interface design so for example the
typical design of some word processors
would never survive the next non-party
if they were used in a computer game if
you have a user interface that hinders
you in the slightest way people get
really really annoyed and don't like
your game then you lose so you have to
optimize your user interface in such a
fashion that the player after playing
the game for let's say about five
minutes no longer recognizes he needs an
external user interface and is in the
game itself if this takes too long or if
it's always be again interrupted this
inside game feeling by saying okay how
can I do this again
you lose so you have a very very strong
urge to interface this to optimize this
computer interface as far as possible
that's a much higher urge then most
other applications
I know another thing is if you design a
user interface for a computer game you
can design it
a new way if you want to write a new
interface for a word processor you
better stick to how things have been
done for years and years and years again
because your secretary wants to like
have their word processors work like
they did yesterday if you are a big
enough company you may break this every
10 years or so but as a game designer
you have a lot of freedom to create a
new user interfaces and you ways of
interacting as long as the gamers can
learn them in game they are perfect so
if you have some kind of new idea how to
open a window some special 3d effects
let there be a billion answers running
on your screen and painting each other
Peaks or something like that you are
free to do this writing user interface
for our word application is quite boring
you get the news - right and you are
done but computer games are maybe like
some military equipment very very driven
hard to get perfect using a faes and
then they are willing to throw overboard
all existing guidelines if you get some
idea how to kill fast I like this
parallel between writing computer games
and have military equipment both are
about blowing things up having this
requirement for sort of perfect user
interfaces in many games you have some
sort of interface for allowing people to
customize the user interface how far
does that go towards well sharing the
effort of creating the perfect user
defense how to what degree can you
integrate third parties or even the
users themselves there are left-handed
people and right-handed people and you
should consider this but this is as far
as it goes
the art of building a good user
interface is a very hard art if I can't
do it myself I don't have the right to
say okay I can't do this let the
customer do it yourself building a good
user interface takes hours and hours
just configuring and tuning the
parameters to the right values this is
no task I can upload on the user so I
think it's a responsibility of every
game creator really every
creator to deliver a good user interface
okay point taken
it's your responsibility so let's well
let's imagine I want to start my own
game company I want to write a game into
salad maybe this is what some of our
listeners are asking themselves now it
sounds like fun
you can be the hero hard-coding have all
the creative freedom so let's say I've
got a garage that I currently don't need
and it were to start my own gaming
company I have the idea for a great game
how do I go about actually getting
started growing in a lot of money yes
that's that's the central point of
writing games you can either do it in a
professional way then you go to a
company then you get a lot of tasks and
then you will find some people using
Microsoft Project and planning what you
are doing I think you can do this this
is a very serious job how to do this and
the other way the garage way is you have
to meet no you need some kind of daytime
job where you can get all your money and
then as an alternative to playing World
of Warcraft's you create a new game in
your free time
and this is a slower approach you still
need a lot of people working together at
least in the starting core team but this
frees you of the commercial pressure in
the very first step starting with the
second step blowing things up no you are
making things bigger you need a lot of
money and then the whole staff of where
venture capital and so on starts but I
really propose started on a small scale
if you can't make a game farmer to be
fun within a small scale you can make it
as colorful and with painted with as
much art as you want it won't make much
more fun so start with a small team with
a vision how to develop it and stay off
the big money until you have an idea
that makes fun to play ok so it's partly
good and used partly bad news you can
sort of get a game that's fun and if you
can't do that you might want to get in
venture capital to finance the graphics
but armed
well what what what I take from what
you're saying is there is no simple way
to create a big scale real
commercial-grade computer game well bad
luck but anyway is there any final words
you'd like to share with our listeners
yes there are um
just do it if you are a gamer that likes
playing computer games and you have
always dreamed of writing your own
computer game do it many of you will
fail many of you will learn a lot of
while they fail many of you will have a
lot of fun while they fail and but some
of you will succeed and you will find
writing computer games is a very
challenging job and has a lot of
benefits well thank you very much you're
welcome as mentioned at the beginning
here is a message from our sponsor
hello excellent job as coach or trainer
brings to us on food biases to map the
surface of bats working remember to
secure zones PMS and meditators and
nurses quantico food is an analyst
because women become symbols you know
give vision vector come from the Heian
technical demands ever program yawn
hints who may alight and offers
mitigating lloyd in the same it was
passed by bring I can expand this
emeritus is Vicki sue I had first man
Mahesh - I was a fire under back turbine
which printers they're showing us here
if I I'd have a feeling the Sun didn't
quit so I listened the Quinton swab I
admit mentioned so are by looking of
Assad and freiheit means ever be
Stephenson veggie dish - which means
because much to wish in English resume
is every station
I met Diaw but I'm from Edmonton asthma
and asthma Hazare - hi Toby over the
Swiss mahabhava tats affirmative devised
a button about Leonov I had was of
ameica of akeeba SS mia moglie which was
a both white hats and weekend Nishan
warriors often our technician visions
passes on a 90 car off
does insurance a hundy cause in our
high-tech github
yeah but heavily feel interesante angry
room here become as if you fail to guard
cutter ostrich with fear and they're
competent coolly does not say fish pose
no does my hot item under CTU team
Lehman Baba in cannot say under chic
leisure activity that causes coach me to
badness because of moogly trainings
morality foon untile about Saudi militia
training on the soda hop confirm
heaviness the opponents of Deneb
available from our line inter vvv was a
punk T in the W put a shower in sing
under Christian vice with obvious thanks
for listening to software engineering
radio if you want more information about
the podcast and all the other episodes
visit our website at se - radio dotnet
if you want to support us you can donate
to the SU radio team by on the website
or you can advertise for se radio for
example by clicking on the Digg reddit
delicious and slash dog buttons to
contact the team lease an email to team
and Su radio net or if it's specific to
an episode please use the comments
facility on the website so other people
can read and react to your comments this
episode of software engineering radio as
well as all other episodes are licensed
under Creative Commons license please
see the website for details thanks to
Charlie crowd and the pot safe music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle